okay we're gonna talk about my tums and
peripheral nerves and answer the
question what motor deficits occur when
you injure a root of the brachial plexus
in contrast to injuring a peripheral
nerve hello everyone my name is dr.
Morton and I'm the noted anatomist so
did as we go through this tutorial the
basic understanding of the brachial
plexus would be necessary and you may
not have to label everything like this
but you should have an understanding and
if you need some help just look at the
link below to take you to a tutorial on
the overview of the brachial plexus now
a Maya tome is my tomes our muscles
supplied by motor neurons from a single
spinal root level and so here the c5 c6
c7 c8 in t1 levels and the actions
associated with those Maya tomes and so
I'm gonna ask a question what peripheral
nerves transport now the motor neurons
from the spinal cord level to the
various muscle groups and so there we
have it we called the brachial plexus
and so here's the c5 Maya tone which is
shoulder a B duction primarily the
deltoid and that shoulder abduction
looks like this from this position to
this position and the axillary nerve is
what innervates the deltoid muscle that
results in shoulder a deduction so the
axillary nerve is what's transporting
motor neurons from the c5 spinal cord
level to the deltoid how about the c6
Maya tone with elbow flexion of the
biceps well that is what elbow flexion
looks like and the biceps muscles
innervated by the musculocutaneous nerve
so muscular taneous nerve takes motor
neurons from the ventral horn cells of
the c6 spinal cord level and is
transporting those motor neurons to the
biceps
how about c7 might own well that's elbow
extension and that's the triceps and it
looks like this from this position to
this position and the radial nerve it's
was transporting c7 motor neurons
what about c8 with wrist flexion well
that's what wrist and finger flexion
looked like from here to here and the
meeting and alder nerves are what are
transporting motor neurons to the flexor
digitorum superficialis and profundus
muscles what about t1 while finger a b
duction looks like that from here to
there and the doors
in Rossi I do that and the owner nervous
was transporting those motor neurons so
let's do a practice question so what
spinal cord level is primarily
responsible for this action and then
there's our Associated segmental spinal
cord levels well that's wrist flexion
which means the c8 spinal cord levels
responsible for it so there are the
wrist flexors flexor carpi radialis
flexor digitorum superficialis flexor
digitorum profundus half of it flexor
digitorum profundus the other half of it
and flexor carpi ulnaris so the wrist
flexor muscles are innervated by motor
neurons these muscles are innervated by
motor neurons that arise from the c8
spinal cord level Shing like that
so what peripheral nerves transport the
motor neurons from the c8 spinal cord
level to these various wrist flexor
muscles so there's the brachial plexus
so what are those two nerves
it's the median and ulnar nerve that are
doing it all right so the wrist flexor
muscles are innervated by motor neurons
that arise from the c8 spinal cord level
and are transported by way of the
meeting in ulnar nerves so peripheral
nerves are muscles that are supplied by
motor neurons from a single peripheral
nerve now these peripheral nerves may
contain more than one spinal cord level
let's do a practice question if the
following neurons those ones were
injured
what would most likely occur all wrist
flexion would be affected no change in
wrist flexion some wrist flexion would
be affected so pause and think about it
for a second and I'm gonna continue if
you just knock out the ulnar nerve some
wrist flexion would be affected because
the flexor carpi radialis superficialis
flexor digitorum superficialis and half
of the FDP
would be okay because the median nerve
is unaffected only the owner
contribution to wrist flexion would be
affected how about this one if the
following neurons there were injured
what would most likely happen pause look
at the choices and think about it I'm
now continuing the answer to this one is
that all wrist flexion would be affected
the reason being look at you've knocked
out all motor neurons coming from c8 so
all those motor
going in the median and ulnar nerves
would be affected so let's look at this
picture these pictures what spinal cord
levels primarily responsible for these
images well there is elbow flexion and
sensation of the thumb and the brachial
radialis reflex well the answer is the
c6 neurological level and so there are
all those neurons associate connecting
back and forth either sensory 2 or motor
from the tissues and spinal cord
so what nerves are now peripheral
branches of the brachial plexus are
transporting these well I mean let's
take a look at that
the one up there for flexion of the
elbow that's musculocutaneous nerve
sensation of the thumb that's median
nerve and brachioradialis reflex both
motor and sensory that's a radial nerve
if the following was injured right there
what would most likely happen pause and
read through those choices and think of
the answer I'm gonna continue the answer
to this is see you would lose sensation
only in the median nerve sensory field
for the thumb that's right there why
well musculocutaneous nerve is
unaffected because elbow flexion is
still able to go because the
musculocutaneous nerve is okay and
brachial radialis reflex is okay because
the radial nerve is not affected how
about if the following injury was here
what would happen pause and think
through this as you look through the
choices I'm going to continue the answer
is loss of the brachioradialis reflex
and why only that
well the musculocutaneous and median
nerves are unaffected so elbow flexion
and sensation of the thumb would be okay
how about if the Fallen injury what if
the injury was there what would most
likely occur pause and read through the
choices and think about it I'm going
forward the answer is basically you're
knocking out the entire c6 neurological
level look at that you knock out the
ventral ramus on c6
you cannot get motor neurons to the
musculocutaneous nerve or through the
radial nerve and you cannot get sensory
neurons from proprioceptors in the
brachioradialis muscle or
sensory neurons from the median nerve of
the thumb now you'll notice then so
that's why I highlighted and underlined
a but then Beast D and E would be
affected but I said lose sensation in
the median nerve sensory field why
didn't I include that what we would
knock out from the c6 level but remember
the median nerve also does your swear
finger which is the c7 dermatome so you
would still be able to get sensory
neurons there okay so now what about
let's do some tracing trace sensory
motor neurons in the median nerve so
there's our median nerve in the
cutaneous field and on the brachial
plexus so let's follow sensory neurons
from the thumb go to the c6 level how
about the middle finger the swear finger
to c7 how about to the c8 spinal cord
level there's our motor neurons going to
the wrist flexors and how about t1 going
to our intrinsic an muscles and then the
median nerve case basically our thenor
muscles you'll hear notice then that the
median nerve has four different segments
of the spinal cord associated with it
but the c6 and c7 are primarily sensory
and the c8 and t1 are primarily motor
how about the ulnar nerve well there's
our older nerve cutaneous field and we
follow the sensation all the way back to
the c8 dermatome level and let's take a
look now the c8 Myatt ohm level that
goes to wrist flexors and then the t1
goes to intrinsic and muscles primarily
everything at hypothenar lumbricals and
so forth so Myatt ohms if you injure a
root or trunk
you're gonna lose strength in its
associated Maya tone if you injure a
peripheral nerve you're gonna lose
strength in all the associated muscles
and that my friends is the Maya tome and
peripheral nerves in a nutshell
[Music]
you